Hello everybody! Thanks for joining us on another Jack author interview. My name is
Mitoaaki Salano, Executive Associate Editor Jack and we are honored to be joined by
Dr. Karen Joy Maddox from Washington University School of Medicine St. Louis.
And today we will have Karen kind of explain about the research original
article that has been pulled to Jack. The title of the article is
Hospitalizations and Mortality Among Medicare Beneficiaries at Cardiovascular
Risk Disruptions and Recovery from the COVID-19 Pandemic. And with that I
would like to have Karen describe Dr. Article. Thank you for joining us, Karen.
First thank you so much for having me. It's an honor to get to chat with you
about this and I also want to go ahead and thank all of my co-authors, particularly
Rishi Waderra and Arji Waken who really played a huge role in bringing this
forward. So to thank all the co-authors as well for making this happen. This is a
labor of love to get it all to the finish line. So I'm thrilled to get to talk
about it a little bit today. So our main question for this paper was trying to
understand what happened sort of not in the peak moments of the pandemic but
really in sort of the couple of years that followed. So 2021 and 2022 as business
kind of got back to normal but we knew that there were still these lingering
effects of the pandemic particularly on beneficiaries with cardiovascular
risk factors or disease. So big picture the goal was essentially to do an
epidemiologic look at the Medicare population and understand among folks with
cardiovascular risk factors or cardiovascular disease what happened in those
couple of years after the peak pandemic in terms of utilization and patient
outcomes. Thank you. I mean some porridge to understand what happened in the
later phase of the pandemic. We kind of know what occurred during the first
year of the pandemic or the two years into the pandemic but we don't really have
too many reports on the later phase. So can you talk about the key findings and
key takeaways from this paper? Sure. So we had we had about 50 million folks in
both the pre-pandemic so 2018-19 and sort of the late pandemic the 2021-22
time frame. So the totality of Medicare beneficiaries fee-for-service and
Medicare Advantage and from the pre-pandemic to late pandemic the populations
were relatively similar except for a big shift toward Medicare Advantage. But
what we found was that utilization and outcomes were actually quite a bit
different in that two year period again post that sort of the peak 2020. So
hospital visits were eight or nine percent lower overall. So if you look at the
hospital curve we're sort of going along at a certain utilization huge drop in
COVID which we've seen documented before and then a recovery but not back up to
the same level as before in terms of hospital utilization. We saw outpatient
visits actually recover back above and part of that was driven by telehealth
right. So we had this new sort of modality for people to access KRCC outpatient
visits bumping along drop and then go up and up above their baseline post not post
COVID post peak COVID. But I think the most concerning thing was we saw also a
pretty sustained increase in mortality. So similarly mortality on a certain trend
big spike during COVID and then continued spikes along with COVID waves such
that the overall mortality among Medicare beneficiaries with cardiovascular
risk factors or disease in that period was about 20 percent higher in sort of a
relative scale depending a little bit on which group you're looking at. So you
know real differences in both utilization and outcomes in that sort of near
post pandemic late pandemic whatever we're going to call that period in that
in that time. Thank you Karen and you spoke about a certain populations about
holding much more vulnerability towards mortality hospitalizations. What did
you find from your these subgroups that you looked into or from the the
Medicare data set? So for the hospital visit rates we found that the decreases
were greatest in rural and socially vulnerable areas based on social
vulnerable social vulnerability index a little bit less so in Medicare
advantage. For the outpatient visits we saw that increased most in the urban
areas is pretty similar by social vulnerability and up most among Medicare
advantage. But then to focus on the mortality again we really saw that the
biggest increase in mortality was among socially vulnerable individuals or
people living in socially vulnerable areas and among Medicare advantage compared
to fee for service beneficiaries. We did not find a big difference in terms of
the mortality increase for rural versus urban. So we looked at that as well but
really the for mortality the social vulnerability and Medicare advantage were
two of the big two of the big differences. Thank you Karen so I think the
listeners are wondering you know why we see this trend and you know we can't
really exactly tell why we don't see the reasons behind the the Medicare data
itself we do have to in some aspects do have to persuade but what do you think
really happened or the discussion over the over the pandemic or the late phase
of the pandemic. Yeah and you can imagine we had the same question when we saw
the the numbers what on earth is happening here and why do we see it so
consistently and persistently. I think there's probably I've sort of bucketed
in my head at least into sort of three different areas and I think each one is
probably contributing I think one that we have only circumstantial evidence for
but you know this is why lots of different types of researchers exist is the
biological there's also perhaps a behavioral and then there's potentially a
systems bucket so to sort of go and order you know biologically we know that
COVID was quite dangerous right COVID itself was quite dangerous and the
aftermath of COVID was quite dangerous there's a study that came out in
Nature Communications quite recently looking at Swedish populations and
showing that the increased risk of death all caused mortality or cardiovascular
death was higher more than a year out and anyone who had previously had COVID so
there's a huge tale of COVID itself that we don't totally understand presumably
something related to inflammation you know every winter I mean I just
rounded for three weeks and we saw flu and COVID and para metanummo whatever
virus is out there right really triggering heart failure and ischemic stroke and
acute am I so there's got to be something biological to sort of how the virus
drove things either acute viruses or the sort of tale of the of the effect not
my scientific area I know people are working on this so I will just say that I
think there's something to that though again as you said we don't know exactly
you know the behavioral piece I think is important too we know there was care
avoidance during COVID and that seemed to persist particularly among women
among people from some racial and ethnic minority groups that may have suffered
from worse access in the first place we don't know whether that translates
into this data set because we can't ask people those questions but I think there's
always a lingering concern that some of the behaviors around care seeking may be
a little bit different access to care may be a little bit different with
backlogs for procedures prevention things like that and then the systems pieces
of you know words were hospitals strained is there something different about
care delivery or about the health care system it's hard to know there's another
paper that just came out and Jam and her medicine about skilled nursing
facility supply showing that it was quite decreased so if you have staffing
problems and skilled nursing facilities and people are you know staying in
the hospital too long what does that do for functional status for mortality
there were just so many things changing at once I don't think we can say that
there's any one sort of you know element that was driving the rest but I do
think it's worth understanding in each of those three buckets what happened to
the degree we can this is you know this is not the last time that we're going to
face some sort of a challenge to the health care system and so I think
understanding what might underlie those is really important thank you Karen I
mean I totally agree I mean looking at these patterns or temple trends across
the pandemic it's really not about you know just what happened it's also about
preparing for the next emergency and I hope it doesn't happen but I mean
sometimes it may happen and so understanding where our health care system is
really vulnerable and where it falls short how we can strengthen those
weak points probably is going to be the you know the very the takeaway and you know
we would have to be prepared for that and I think you know that's that's what
it really truly illustrates in your article and I really encourage our
listeners to go take the beautiful figures and of course the article itself
it's full of the content over the last the four five years and then you know
it's it's really to understand where we fall short in cardiovascular health and
who's going to be the most vulnerable population in the US well thank you for
joining us Karen and thank you all listeners for listening until next time
take care thank you